# **ANDREW LEACH**

Edmonton, AB +1 780-217-2453

leach.andrew@gmail.com

@andrew\_leach

leach-econ

leachandrew

aleach.ca

aleach.ca/charts

## Economist. Data Scientist. Policy Analyst. Academic leader.

I am an energy and environmental economist and Associate Professor at the University of Alberta, where I direct the CABREE research centre and an interdisciplinary electricity research group. My research spans energy and environmental economics with a focus on climate change policies and the law. I have advised federal and provincial governments and provided policy analysis to public- and private-sector clients. I am also an avid data scientist, exploring ways to summarize and visualize energy and economic indicators. I am a prolific writer, with over 200 bylines in major Canadian outlets.

#### **EXPERIENCE**

2011 - present Associate Professor, Alberta School of Business, University of Alberta

Faculty member in the Natural Resources, Energy and Environment group, Academic Director of

CABREE Research Centre, and Future Energy Systems grant holder.

2020 - present Sessional Instructor, Faculty of Law, University of Alberta

Developed and delivered a course on environmental law and policy.

**Economics and Policy Consultant**, 2006 - present

Environmental policy development and evaluation. Policy advisor to federal and provincial govern-

ments. Expert witness on energy, economic, and regulatory files.

2006 - 2011 Assistant Professor, Alberta School of Business, University of Alberta

Faculty member in the Natural Resources, Energy and Environment group.

2003 - 2006 Assistant Professor/Professeur Adjoint, HEC Montréal

Faculty member in the Institute of Applied Economics.

### **EDUCATION**

2019 - 2020 LLM (Constitutional Law), University of Alberta

Thesis examined the constitutional anchors for climate change policies under the POGG, Trade and

Commerce, and Criminal Law powers of the federal government.

1999 - 2003 Ph.D. (Economics), Queen's University

Thesis focussed on applying numerical methods to examine the economics of climate change

policy, including distributional issues and the impacts of uncertainty and learning on optimal policy.

1998 - 1999 MA (Economics), University of Guelph

Focus on environmental, resource, and labour economics.

1994 - 1998 B.Sc. (Environmental Science), University of Guelph Major: Environmental Economics and Policy.

#### **WORK PRODUCT**

**Publications Academic Publications** aleach.ca/publications

An on-line archive of my academic publications.

Data Data and visualization project archive aleach.ca/projects

Visualization A public archive of data aggregation, collection and visualization tools.

Opinion **Opinion Archive** aleach.ca/opinion

An archive of my public writing, Parliamentary Committee testimony and more.

#### **LANGUAGES HOBBIES NON PROFIT**

English - native I am an avid cyclist, occasional runner, French - proficient downhill and cross-country skier, hockey

player, and hobbyist woodworker.

Board of Directors, REACH Edmonton and Edmonton Juventus Cycling Club. Past Board Member, River Valley Alliance and Economic Society of Northern Alberta.